<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a person of quality, to a principal peer of the realm, now sitting in Parliament occasioned by the present debate upon the penal lawes.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12926160</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12926160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 986:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a person of quality, to a principal peer of the realm, now sitting in Parliament occasioned by the present debate upon the penal lawes.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611 [i.e. 1661]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.H.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95528:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM A Perſon of Quality, TO A Principal PEER of the REALM, Now Sitting in PARLIAMENT. Occaſioned by the preſent DEBATE UPON THE Penal Lawes.</p>
            <q>Viva la Libertè.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year M.DC.XI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:95528:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95528:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER from a Perſon of Quality, to a principal Peer of the REALM, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the weighty Affairs of this Nation, which your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> like another <hi>Atlas,</hi> hath hitherto ſo happily ſet your Shoulder to; the indulgent care you have always had, to favour tender conſciences, hath always been moſt Glorious and Remarkable. From thence, My Lord, I have taken confidence, amidſt the Crowd of thoſe many other cares that oppreſſe you, to offer to your Lordſhip ſomething, though it be but the poor oblation of <hi>Virgils</hi> Shepheard, <hi>Mitia Poma &amp; Caſtaneas Nuces,</hi> in the behalf of that poor, diſtreſs'd, and almoſt deplor'd Party amongſt us, who have for theſe laſt hundred years, layn under a more bloody and inhumane perſecution, than ever before was heard of amongſt Chriſtians. And becauſe that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is perpetual, where the Lord layeth the Foundation, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip cannot do a more Charitable and Heroical Act, then to be in ſome ſort, a <hi>Mecaenas</hi> to that Religion, and to Sollicit his Sacred Majeſty, and the preſent Parliament, for a fair Liberty at leaſt, if not privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for it; and that His Majeſty like another <hi>Cyrus,</hi> may be pleaſed to procure that <hi>Iſrael</hi> may return, and build up their Temple; ſo ſhall they be obliged to pray for the Life of our <hi>Cyrus,</hi> aad to write His
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95528:3"/>Majeſties name, upon their Altars and Church Dores, and that <hi>Deus illis haec Otia fecit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not a more common than true Rule, I'm ſure it ſeldome fails, that <hi>Malus Cuſtos diuturnitatis Metus,</hi> and therefore <hi>Tacitus</hi> could not deſcribe the Tyranny of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> but he muſt declare the Marks and properties thereof, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Delatorum Autoritas magna, laeſae Majeſtatis crimen frequens objicitur, ac boni cujuſque viri invadendi ac tollendi praetextus eſt;</hi> and he addeth, <hi>frequens accuſatio, &amp; in quovis crimine adjuncta de laeſa Majeſtate Principis.</hi> Nothing ſhews more evidently when Authority inclines towards Tyranny, then the multitude of Promoters, Purſuivants, Catchpoles, continual infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and the name of Treaſon made as a Livery to put upon all offences, and <hi>tot eſſe delatores in Repub.</hi> he makes as a certain Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptome, of a diſeaſed and a decaying State. In former ages, I am ſure, thoſe were ever held to be the beſt, and moſt Godly Laws, that were leaſt Sanguinary, and yet maintained order, all others were accounted but meer <hi>Phalariſmes,</hi> and to be <hi>le ges Draconis. Seneca</hi> who liv'd under a Terrible Tyrant, found by experience, that <hi>frequens Vindicta paucorum odium reprimit, omnium irritat,</hi> often puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments provoke more ill blood then they ſuppreſs: which may be an Error, ſo as a general Rule, to which there may be too much excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but this I am ſure is notorious, and an undoubted Soleciſme in State, to puniſh moſt crimes with the penalty of Treaſon. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima ſupplicia ſuppliciis ultimis ponat, ut nemo pereat, niſi quem perire etiam pereuntis interſit,</hi> in a good Government indeed, none ſhould be put to death,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 2.26.</note> but ſuch whoſe own very intereſt it is, ſo to be put to death. The Speech of <hi>Abner</hi> to <hi>Joab</hi> is hugely remarkable to this purpoſe; <hi>Num uſque ad internecionem hujus Mucro deſaeviet? an ignoras quod periculoſa eſt deſperatio? uſꝑ quo non dicis populo ut omittat perſequi fratres ſuos?</hi> Shall the Sword devour for ever? Know'ſt thou not, that it is not a little dangerous to force a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration? How long ſhall it be then ere thou bid the people return from perſecuting of their Brethren? It is both good counſel and good example. <hi>Germanicus</hi> is noted to have wept when he ſaw the ſlaughter of the Souldiers of the <hi>Legions</hi> that mutiny'd, <hi>non Medicinam illam, ſed Cladem appellavit,</hi> and call'd it not a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine but a Maſſacre. Nor can I think that all pity dy'd with <hi>Germanicus,</hi> or that there are not many, nay moſt in <hi>England</hi> mov'd with the Butchery of ſome perſons here meerly for their Faith, and Profeſſion, though barbarouſly couch'd under the name of Treaſon. I know it is the property of Commiſeration, to be touch'd rather
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95528:3"/>with the Calamity it ſeeth, than to examine the Cauſe which it ſeeth not. Yet my only comfort is, that your Lordſhip will offer the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of theſe things, to a far greater Emperour than <hi>Germanicus,</hi> and a Prince of much more eminently tender bowels of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. So I ſhall be bold to urge one argument more for commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration, from the example of a Pagan Prince <hi>Marcus Aurelius;</hi> though the old Law was ſtill in force, and ſtrictly obſerv'd at <hi>Rome, Deos peregrinos we colunto,</hi> that no ſtrange Gods ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, yet he permitted alwayes Toleration to Chriſtians, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> aſſures us. Then <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Gratian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. in Apol. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperours, were content to tolerate the <hi>Arrians,</hi> known to be the moſt real Enemies of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Joſephus</hi> a Jew noteth of <hi>Omias Megalita,</hi> the ſame Permiſſion,<note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> to continue Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood, for the Peace of the State. The <hi>Venetians</hi> ſuffer the <hi>Jews</hi> to live amongſt them, as the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did the <hi>Moors,</hi> till neceſſity forced him to expel them. How much more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will it appear, to Tolerate our Brethren of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Religion, who are undeniably <hi>Filii Chriſti,</hi> Sons of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the <hi>Mother Church,</hi> which we in <hi>England</hi> uſe to call the <hi>ſurer</hi> ſide. For it is a verity undoubtable, ſo far as ever I could find, that that Church was formerly the Reverend Mother of all <hi>Chriſtianiſme,</hi> and the moſt ancient Law-maker, and Judge heretofore of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</p>
            <p>It is a moſt falſe Propoſition, and proceeded doubtleſs from Gall and Spleen, that <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are altogether unſociable, and that they cannot live with us, nor any ſort of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> in one Kingdome or Common-wealth, without Jars and Tumults; and laſtly, which is given out onely to breed an exulceration in the hearts of the people, againſt thoſe of that Religion, they affirm, that to give the leaſt connivance to them, is a ſin no leſs than dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. This I know is blown daily from the mad, turbulent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Pulpits of ſome <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> who indeed, if any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are juſtly to fall under that cenſure, ſhould not themſelves have Toleration any where; whoſe Phrenetical, giddy zeal, will be confin'd within no circle of order, but ever contemning all Law and Law-givers, endevour to domineer, and rule as <hi>Tranſcendents</hi> over all <hi>Kings, States, Princes</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in the world. But I hope theſe few Conſiderations following, may qualifie a little, if not cool the extravagant heat of ſuch indiſcreet and hair-brain'd zelots, and confute their weak, and truly unchriſtian ſuppoſition of incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95528:4"/>
            <p>And firſt, if we look back to former ages, we ſhall find, that from the <hi>Saxons</hi> to King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, to be a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> was neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any Bar to Loyalty, or Obedience to Civil Government. Nor can any man deny, but that <hi>France, Spain, Italy,</hi> the <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> have ever accounted, and do ſtill, him as the beſt affected Subject, and leaſt dangerous to the Civil State, who is the beſt affected to that Religion; and certainly, if to be a <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> did ever breed or engender any ſuch ill blood in the Body Politick, or ſecret infection of Diſloyalty, as theſe men would fain perſwade the world it does; and ſo muſt be in regard of the State, <hi>malum aliquod in ſe,</hi> and naturally; then upon the general tryal of ſo many Nations, and in ſo many Ages, it would have been ſure diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, and detected of that noxious imperfection, which it never has before ſtood charged withal, neither in all thoſe forraign Countreys, not as heretofore, ſo not at any time ſince, in <hi>England.</hi> Nay, to the eternal glory of that truly Noble and Honorable Party, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of all their Adverſaries, I dare ſay, that there is not one perſon of conſideration amongſt them all to be found out, that was at the ſame time a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and in arms againſt His Majeſty that now is, or His moſt glorious <hi>Father.</hi> But on the contrary, it is plain, that they did all expoſe themſelves, their lives, fortunes, and families in His Majeſties Service, to as much hazard as any whoſoere they were in <hi>England;</hi> nay, for the preſervation of thoſe very Laws, by the force of which, they were to ſuffer a moſt ſavage per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p>But yet the Antagoniſts of this moſt Rational and Chriſtian Liberty deſired for thoſe excellent perſons, I fear will hardly yet reſt ſatisfied; for they ſtand ſo high in their own conſiſtories, and yet higher in their own opinions, that nothing but miracle can be thought capable to abate the Edge of their moſt phrenetick fury. However they may pleaſe to remember, <hi>chacun a ſon Tour,</hi> nor can they I am ſure forget, how that from the Time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and ſince him, Religion has had its changes, and what God pleaſeth to determine, man muſt obey: they that are now in <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> may be hereafter <hi>ſicut erat in Principio:</hi> they ought therefore to live, and to continue with all men in Chriſtian charity and amity, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, that the bonds of religious Unity, are ſo to be ſtrenghtned, as that the bonds of humane Society be not diſſolved. At <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in the time of our Saviour Chriſt, there were two Sects much different in Religion, and yet did live ſociably together, and without offence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95528:4"/>to Church or State, which were the <hi>Phariſaei</hi> and the <hi>Sadducaei:</hi> and they were not only, not men of one Religion, and ſo differing only in Rites and Orders, but they were men of very oppoſite per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, and in main fundamentals too. No man I believe will doubt, but that the <hi>Saduces</hi> were notorious <hi>Hereticks,</hi> for they deny'd the Reſurrection of the Dead, and the Immortality of the Soul (an Article of our Belief, and the Foundation of all our Hope and Faith:) that there was a fierce oppoſition between them and the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> is evident by that in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Exurgens Pontifex &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Saducaei qui cum eo erant, &amp;c.</hi> Then the High Prieſt roſe up, and all they that were with him, which is the <hi>Sect of the Saduces,</hi> &amp;c. and again, <hi>Sciens Paulus quod una pars eſſet Saducaeorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 23.</note> 
               <hi>altera Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeorum exclamavit,</hi> &amp;c. But when <hi>Paul</hi> perceived that the one part were <hi>Saduces,</hi> and the other <hi>Phariſees,</hi> &amp;c. Thus it is plain, that theſe parties were ſufficiently oppoſite, and did often contradict one another; the <hi>Saduces</hi> maintained the Temple of <hi>Gerizim,</hi> and agreed with the <hi>Samaritans</hi> to ſacrifice there, contrary to the Law, and to the prejudice of the Temple at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> The people follow'd the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> applauded the <hi>Saduces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Segon. de Republic. Hebraea. p. <hi>538.</hi> Epiphan. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> Joſeph. l. <hi>18.</hi> Antiq.</note> and both were Hereſies, as <hi>Sigonius</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> do moſt clearly teſtify, and yet all that City was divided into theſe two Sects, in the time of <hi>Herodes Antippus,</hi> as <hi>Joſephus</hi> aſſures us, and yet did they live very quietly together as to the Civil Government, without Diſcord, Riots, or Tumults. To come home to our later Times, we may begin with <hi>Swiſſerland;</hi> and though <hi>Zuinglius</hi> was a rough, violent, and ſeditious fellow, and by arms ſought to compel the five Pages to the Religion of <hi>Bern</hi> and <hi>Zurich,</hi> yet by agreement all was pacifi'd, and to this day they have their particular Churches in their ſeveral Towns, and maintain their mutual Liberties, the Common-wealth of the <hi>Cantons,</hi> all Contributions, Confederations, Traffick, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety together, and ſometime preach, nay communicate like good fellows, in the ſame Churches and Pulpits. To paſs over <hi>Suevia,</hi> and the Lower Provinces of <hi>Germany</hi> (where though <hi>Lutheraniſme</hi> before and <hi>Calviniſme</hi> ſince hath very much prevailed) thoſe <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> yet that are, remain undiſturb'd. The famous Kingdome of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Empire of <hi>Muſco,</hi> have thought it neceſſary to ſuffer the Religious <hi>Vried</hi> in their Dominions and Countreys, both to take away all Domeſtical quarrels, and by a general unity (as a brazen wall) to fortifie themſelves againſt the common Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> the <hi>Turk.</hi> And ſhall <hi>England</hi> now ſo far degenerate from its ancient glory &amp; vertue, as to go to ſchool for civility to a rude
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95528:5"/>
               <hi>Swiſs,</hi> or Swiniſh debauch'd <hi>Dutchman?</hi> Shew more Barbariſme than a <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> or more unnaturalneſs than a <hi>Polonian?</hi> who reſerve the blood of their Neighbours, to be ſhed with Honour in the Field againſt their common Enemies, rather then by Tyranny at home, to weaken their own body; <hi>Germany</hi> alſo may be a ſufficient example, that ſuch a toleration is moſt expedient, and that it is both poſſible and faiſible, that two, or more different religions, may live together in peace. Let theſe <hi>Conſiſtorians</hi> call to mind, how quietly the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have ſuffered, and converſt with the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lately ſprung up there (for above a hundred years together) till they with the <hi>Swedes</hi> were pleas'd to diſturb their own peace, and the Tranquillity of that moſt beautiful <hi>Empire.</hi> And ſure <hi>Charls</hi> the Fifth, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> who indulg'd ſo much liberty to thoſe Religions, as they were great and wiſe Princes, ſo were they as provident like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and merciful. Their ground too was the ſame with ours, <hi>Salus Populi ſupremae lex eſto,</hi> the peoples Safety ought to be the Supream Law, and therefore they ordered, that <hi>Caveret utraque pars, ne in ſuis dominiis quemquam ad ſuae religionis profeſſionem cogat, aut revocet, aut depellat contra ipſius conſcientiam, à religione quam profitetur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dreſſerus.</note> So ſaith <hi>Dreſſerus,</hi> that both ſides ſhould beware of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing any man to his Religion, of recalling, or driving any man againſt his conſcience from the Religion that he profeſſeth: and afterwards confidently adds againſt thoſe that are ſo preciſely ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, <hi>Nec hic metuo eorum reprehenſionem, qui putant non niſi unam Religionem tolerandam,</hi> Nor fear I at all their diſpleaſure, who will think that there ought to be but one Religion tolerated, for conſcience cannot be compell'd, it may be perſwaded. But that I may not be tedious, I ſhall conclude all my Inſtances with the fair and flouriſhing Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi> How often and how mercifully did the <hi>French Kings</hi> grant their <hi>Edicts of Pacification?</hi> and to what conditions were they contented to deſcend, only to preſerve Life and avoid Bloodſhed of their people? Witneſſe the old Articles of Peace granted for the Liberty of conſcience,<note place="margin">La Val. l. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>141.</hi> Pig. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Poploneir l. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> ſet down by <hi>La Vall</hi> and divers others, wherein they have a general freedome to preach in all parts of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. and yet theſe were <hi>Huguenots;</hi> men of the <hi>Conſiſtorian Religion,</hi> Factious, Boutefeus, and in truth, the very ſhame of <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Yet would the poor <hi>Roman Catholicks of England,</hi> be right glad to participate a ſhare of ſuch Graces, as they enjoy there, though there is no wiſe man ſure, but muſt think that they deſerve them much better. They poor Souls, with prayers and tears do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95528:5"/>daily to His Majeſty and the Parliament for ſuch a Liberty: Thoſe in <hi>France</hi> were always ſtriving to wreſt it by Force, and the bloody violence of a Presbyterian Spirit. They again had a <hi>Rochel,</hi> a <hi>Montanban,</hi> or a <hi>Montpelier</hi> for their refuge; theſe in <hi>England,</hi> had no other retreat but the <hi>Gatehouſe,</hi> the <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>Newgate.</hi> For theſe in <hi>England,</hi> all Princes and States have long interceded, and do ſtill; They in <hi>France</hi> had never any other Interceſſour, but their own Arms for them. Now to conclude all, ſeeing the great <hi>Turk</hi> permitteth <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to live freely in his Dominions, ſeeing the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Example of the greateſt Princes and States in <hi>Europe</hi> doth ſet it forward, the poor <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> hope they ſhall not far, the worſe, for their patience and obedience, which deſerveth more. Their only ambition is to be accounted good Servants to God, and Loyal Subjects to His Majeſty, and their only humble Suit to His Majeſty now is, <hi>Hanc animam concede mihi, tua caetera ſunto.</hi> Give them their Souls, great Sir, take you the reſt.</p>
            <p>Thus far under your Lordſhips favour, I have been bold to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the behalf of the tender Conſciences of thoſe, who have ſuffered moſt in that kind of any <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the World; but now two Objections ſeem to obſtruct all that has been hitherto ſpoken in the argument. And methinks at this Inſtant, I hear a wellmouth'd <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to open againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> where only this liberty is denyed; and why ſhould they have Liberty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who will give none to others? To this I ſhall be bold to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate, that there are but two ſorts of good Policy, in order to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The one is to keep firm and faſt to one Religion, where there is but one, nor ever has been more; and with all care to keep out all others, be they good or bad, this I ſay in order to the Civil State, is a moſt neceſſary peice of Policy. For nothing embroyles a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or State ſooner, than the Diverſities of Religions, eſpecially if ſome particular ones be forbidden. For the Prohibition of ſome, creates faction in the hearts of the ſuppreſt, unleſſe hindered by very extraordinary grace, and faction ever pretends zeal of Spirit, which if it become Conqueror ſhews no mercy, if ſubdued, no patience: however mutinous and a boutefeu, which join'd with the other two, called curioſity and ſingularity, are the three furyes, that torment the World at this inſtant, that <hi>Triceps Cerberus,</hi> that ſets open Hell gates, to fill the World with Impoſtors, Seducers, and Calumniation. Now to Faction and her adherents, Sedition is an unſeparable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, which ſtreightways marryes it ſelf to Schiſm, and thereupon it is, that all Magiſtrates and Laws are reſiſted, and that with violence, for there is no War ſo paſſionate, as the War of Conſcience. The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95528:6"/>
               <hi>Inquiſition</hi> therefore is politickly to be commended, for keeping ſtrict Watch and Ward, yea with fire and Sword to keep out all other Religions from thence, where there never was any other, then what they ſtill profeſſe. The ſecond good Policy in relation to Religion is, where by the negligence of Governours, or ſome other unhappineſs, ſeveral Religions have got footing, to give an equal liberty to all, as at preſent in the <hi>Low Countries, France, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. Now this equality of liberty takes away all heart-burning, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would burſt forth into faction, and that into ſedition, to the publick diſturbance. So it is plain, that it is the prohibition and perſecution of ſome one or two Religions, not the perſecution of all but one; or a univerſal Toleration of all indifferently, that can offend a Kingdome; and ſuch a Policy of a general liberty, were to be wiſhed here amongſt us, ſince we cannot have the other: For in very deed, it is altogether as impoſſible to root out any one Religion by a perſecution, as to put out a fire by blowing of it.</p>
            <p>The next and greateſt objection, that I muſt be bold under your Lordſhips Conduct, to encounter, looks very big upon me indeed, that it is not for their Religion, that Prieſts and their Entertainers die, but plain matter of Treaſon. I muſt here beſeech the Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to let us know, how it comes to paſs, that it ſhould be Treaſon to be a Prieſt, or Capital for a Gentleman to entertain ſuch a one in his houſe, to ſerve the neceſſities of his Conſcience? or who made it ever to be ſo, either in this, or any other Countrey in the world, before the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> Whereby it is apparent that it is not <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> but <hi>quia prohibitum</hi> it muſt be ſo. And then to the amazement of the whole world, that Vocation muſt be made Treaſon, which was only wont here in <hi>England</hi> to ſit in the Chair of Government, and by whoſe Oracles and Decrees, the people of this Land, were onely wont to be directed both in <hi>Chancery, Rolls,</hi> and all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi> It would be thought, I am confident, a very ſtrange thing, that any Parliament, ſhould make it to be Treaſon, for any man to wear a <hi>Barre-gown,</hi> or to be known to be a <hi>Graduate</hi> in that Profeſſion: Will it not be a more incredible thing to poſterity, that ſo wiſe a Nation as this, ſhould run counter to themſelves, all Law and Reaſon, upon ſuch a ſuddain, as to make that Treaſon by Act of Parliament, which ſo generally, ſo perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and ſo anciently, hath been honour'd, and approved by all Laws. Was not Prieſthood us'd and exerciſed by the Patriarchs under the Law of Nature? Eſtabliſh'd by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and the Law of God? Continued yet in Chriſt, who was himſelf a Prieſt for ever, after
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95528:6"/>the order of <hi>Melchizedek?</hi> and never apparently repeal'd by him, or any new Decree under his Grace and the Goſpel. Was there ever any Nation that had a Worſhip of a Deity, and acknowledg'd a God, without their Prieſt? By the Wiſdome of former Ages we find that Religion and Prieſthood were ever taken to be like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> Twins, born and bred, laughing and weeping, beginning and ending together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And muſt this ſacred Function now, that is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and reverenced over all the world, by our Laws, that are unknown to all the World beſides, be made a peice of Treaſon, here? It is no wonder indeed, if ſuch new made Treaſons, as has been afore cited out of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> did preſage a fall, or diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Power, which made them to be ſo: and it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that the Auſpicious repealing of ſuch, will foreſpeak aſwell the growing up of a moſt flouriſhing <hi>Empire.</hi> Over and above all this, it h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s been ever held againſt the Wiſdome and Policy of this Nation, to fetter themſelves with too many ſhackles of Treaſon; and therefore as 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. at the petition of the Subjects, the King did declare and determine what ſhould be taken and judged for Treaſon, by the Common Laws of the Realm, ſo 1. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. it was confirm'd and eſtabliſhed, that nothing hereafter ſhould be judg'd Treaſon, otherwiſe than was expreſs'd by that of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and though divers Actions were ſtrain'd up to Treaſon for a time, which indeed were not ſo, nor within the liſt of the 15. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. as that of <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. the taking and ſurprizing of perſons and goods in <hi>Wales,</hi> ſo to ſtand for the ſpae of ſeven yeras only, and 8. of <hi>H.</hi> 6. burning of houſes, and 22. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. poyſoning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which of their own nature, and ſimply were not Treaſon, and therefore had a limitation of time annexed to them: Yet prudently all ſuch former Acts were repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and made voyd, 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. for a more merciful and indifferent proceeding with Subjects, that the Remedy might not prove more dangerous than the Diſeaſe. And now muſt an eternal Treaſon be branded upon the ſacred'ſt of Functions? and no leſs than the moſt infamous and diſmal word invented, like a <hi>Meduſa's</hi> face to terrifie poor Chriſtians from their Conſciences, Faith and Profeſſion? <hi>Sed ſatius eſt pertranſire Calamitatem publicam.</hi> And yet the great and Chriſtian magnmimity, that all the noble perſons of this perſwaſion, have always expreſs'd, eſpecially in theſe late moſt calamitous times of fiery tryal indeed, is not a little remarkable: when no day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented them leſs then moſt diſmal horrors, deſtructions of themſelves, wives, children and families, and on every ſide, moſt terrible images of death, yet they always ſtood ſtedfaſt to, and unmovable from their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95528:7"/>Principles of Religion; a very inconſiderable number of them ſtarting aſide like a broken bow; in lieu of every one of whom too, they got into their Church, then in the midſt of all their miſeries, more than a thouſand; ſo mightily does the barbarous and inhumane perſecution of any one party, encreaſe its number. Nor was their integrity to God, and loyalty to Religion more obſervable, than their fidelity to His Majeſty, amidſt all the artifices, as well as menaces, of the moſt ſubtil and miſchievous Tyrants, that ever the earth bore. And why then ſhould not theſe moſt honorable Perſons receive ſome Acts of Grace and favour now, and with as much reaſon, as thoſe penalties were exercis'd upon them then in thoſe times, or impos'd upon them at firſt? For it is plain, that there was nothing but fears and jelouſies that were the occaſions of their firſt infliction: Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> having been declared, by three Popes ſucceſſively, and our own Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament to be illegitimate; and that great and moſt incomparable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, His Majeſties great Grandmother, <hi>Mary Queen of Scots, and Dowager of France,</hi> ſtanding at that time in competition with her in the eye of the world, as the juſt Heir of the Crown, who (by the way, was entirely a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and ſo all that party then in <hi>England,</hi> fell into ſuſpicion of an adherence too much to her intereſt; which to avoyd, was the grand reaſon, why this perſecution of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> here in <hi>England</hi> was firſt invented, and the ſuppreſſion of the whole party endevoured by the <hi>Cecilian</hi> policy of thoſe times, and yet we never find that the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> did then, or ſince knit themſelves upon any account of diſturbance here; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary we know that they have been always ready to aſſert His Majeſties Intereſt, not only againſt Rebels and Traitors at home (though to the ſupport of thoſe Laws, as aforeſaid, which have hitherto prov'd their particular ruin) but all enemies whatſoever abroad, even againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf or King of <hi>Spain,</hi> when His Majeſty ſhall ſo pleaſe to command them, and ſo much Loyalty they have been always ready to ſwear to likewiſe, and ſtill are, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf ſhall never be able to withdraw them from their Allegiance to His ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing that by His Majeſties, and the Parliaments great care and prudence, there is a debate admitted for the regulation of thoſe ſcandalous Laws, and ſince it is manifeſtly neceſſary, that as Sails, ſo Laws are to be turn'd, and as occaſion, time, circumſtance, and reaſon of State ſhall direct, either to be altered or revoked, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as it is plain, that upon worldly reſpects, thoſe Acts have paſs'd in former Parliaments, to try what operation and cure they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95528:7"/>would work in the State, and if they prove fruitleſſe Medicines, or as moſt emperical purgations, too violent (and fitter to kill then to cure) then to be repealed; for as they were made for the fears and jealouſies of thoſe times, ſo by the grace and mercy of theſe times, (when they are both prov'd to have been cauſeleſſe) they may with honour be cancell'd, if His Majeſty and the Parliament ſhall ſo pleaſe; to whoſe gracious conſideration, I moſt humbly beſeech Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to offer theſe few Lines, and as Petitions rather then reaſons, nor ſo much to arrogate juſtice, as to implore mercy, and ſeeing alſo that the Caſe of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and His Majeſty that now is, is far different, your Lordſhip would be pleaſed to Petition His Majeſty for theſe poor trouble Souls, and procure a grace for them, that was never denyed by any Chriſtian Kings or States to their Subjects, for occaſions of State, and to ſtop that unnatural iſſue of blood, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thoſe cruel Laws, and ſtay a little thoſe paſſionate humors, and malicious oppoſitions of ſuch, as are adverſaries to that Grace, and the Lord Almighty, who hath raiſed you, to enable you for ſo great a work. Your Lordſhip and the Parliament, cannot but out of your great Wiſdomes have obſerv'd, that too ſevere a perſecution makes men deſperate, <hi>non coercet ſed provocat Violentia,</hi> and too heavy a hand upon thoſe whom the Law caſts down, ſhews a will rather to oppreſſe the offender, then to cure the offence. It is the greateſt Honour to Kings, that their mercy like that of the Almighty, is more eminent then their juſtice, and that their Benches and Courts, can witneſſe more compaſſion then Severity. For he that ſets open the Priſon Dores, in ſo wiſe and gracious a manner, meaneth not to conquer the hearts and conſciences of his people by torments, but to win them by mercy and ſweetneſſe. If the ancient <hi>Aphoriſme</hi> of State be to be reſpected, it hath been ever in ſuch caſes, the Wiſdom of the greateſt Princes, <hi>Punire raro</hi> to puniſh but ſeldome, it was aſcribed as a Title of Honour to <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar, nunquam civilem ſanguinem fudiſſe,</hi> never to have ſhed his peoples blood. Clemency is a Vertue, ſometimes of as great policy as piety, becauſe it begets Love, and Love breeds Loyalty, commands the very Soul, and lays the body at the Feet of the obliger; Mercy kindles Fire and Zeal in the hearts of Subjects. Pity and Toleration as they make the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the offenders greater, ſo it makes them repent to have offended him, who hath ſo obliged them, the reaſon is infallible in all noble Spirits, <hi>Fidelem ſi putaveris, facies,</hi> believe and you make a faithful friend, for the true Gallant Soul ever accounts it the greateſt injury to be diſtruſted.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95528:8"/>
            <p>The poor <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> upon theſe grounds, hope that their ancient and tryed patience and fidelity, ſhall ſo move His Majeſty, and thoſe that he has ſet at the Stern to govern affairs, that they ſhall be now refreſht and eas'd, as they may with a breath, and that they may find at laſt the warmth and comfort of the Sun-ſhine again in <hi>England,</hi> and that their humble ſupplications ſhall be granted, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd with the ſervices of ſo many honorable perſons, and ſign'd with the blood of ſo many of their Martyrs: That though we meet them not in Churches, we may yet meet them cheerfully in our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets; for though they differ from us in Religion, they will agree well with us in Obedience; their bodies will be ever at His Majeſties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, if we do but leave their ſouls of God: and all this happineſs both to them and us, I can no way deſpair of, if your Lordſhip pleaſe to become their Interceſſor, in whoſe great Breaſt, compaſſion ever kept the higheſt ſeat, as it became it beſt: and be confident my Lord, that the obtaining of this lawful favour and Tolleration for theſe poor afflicted Souls, will be a work equal in glory, to any of your Lordſhips moſt illuſtrious Actions, and will raiſe you up, by your Charity, ſo many degrees higher towards heaven, as erect eternal Trophies to your Honour upon earth, and thoſe as great, as ever were, or can be written in the <hi>Records of Fame.</hi> And ſo as His Majeſty came unto the Helm, and aſcended the Throne of theſe Kingdoms with Triumph, Glory and Applauſe, He ſhall end the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of his days, with the general <hi>Plaudite</hi> of the whole world: Nay, all this will follow beſides, as the fruits and effects of His Majeſties good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards the poor <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> Peace within, and Honour without; Love at home, Reſpect abroad; and ſo ſhall be made a concord of diſcords, an union of diviſions, and a religious contention on all ſides, for devotion and a good life; for peaceable converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, obedience to Magiſtrates, excellency of Learning, who ſhall do moſt good in the State, and deſerve the prize; and ſuch an <hi>Eutopia</hi> can onely His Majeſty make in <hi>England,</hi> who will deſerve the Olive branches for Mercy, Peace and Goodneſs, as well as the Laurel, for Victory, Wiſdome, Government and Conſtancy (the Crown of all:) ſo I beſeech your Lordſhip to accept and pardon this preſumption, and continue your favours to</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(MY LORD)</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt obedient Servant, <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 17. 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95528:8"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY haſt had almoſt made me overpaſs one very conſiderable ſcruple, that I have heard frequently injected, to the prejudice of that poor oppreſt Party; which is, that they did only ſerve His Majeſty in the late War, in their own defence, and caeme to the King with a <hi>Cum nemini,</hi> &amp;c. as they ſay. On the contrary, I can ſay on my own knowledge, that they were extremely courted by that <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and proffer'd the perfect abolition of the Penal Laws, ſo they would ſide with them, and effectively proſecute their Rebellion. It was not therefore Intereſt but Conſcience, that engaged them in His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Cauſe. And truly upon the matter, it may be ſaid, that they ſerv'd His Majeſty, whether he would or no, for they could obtain no Commiſſion at all from him, till a Commiſſion granted to one of them, by name Sir <hi>Arth. Aſhton,</hi> from the Rebell Party, was produced: And then His Majeſty thought fit, not to ſcruple the commiſſionating of any of them; all this, my Lord, is known truth, which your Lordſhip may pleaſe to accept likewiſe from</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(MY LORD)</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Devoted Humble Servant, <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
